Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, so we're דף daf behind,
so for today's דף daf is סמך גימל Samach Gimmel and we
pick up at the very bottom of סמך ב עמוד ב Samach
Bet Amud Bet and תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, three lines on the
bottom left, word on the line, and we had done some very
important discussion yesterday about the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru u'revu
and about and specifically about the idea of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
about not just stopping at two, but we had a whole discussion
about how much of an obligation that was or how much that
was מנהג דרך ארץ. minhag derech eretz. And now the גמרא Gemara
is in the middle of a discussion about the importance of marriage,
obviously from here a man's perspective, and we have seen two schools
attributed to בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. בבל Bavel is
something of more intrinsic value
of שמחה simcha and wholeness and and blessing;
it's an essential good. And the what's attributed to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael of more of an instrumental about preventing sin and allowing the
husband to learn תורה, Torah, but we did point out the irony
that most of the other sources in indicate that the actual the
schools were reversed and having something to do with attitudes toward leaving
the home and learning תורה Torah in בבל Bavel versus ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, polygamy, monogamy, and so on. That was a quick summary
of yesterday. So, תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: האוהב את אשתו כגופו, ha'ohev
et ishto k'gufo, a man who loves his wife as himself, ומכבדה
יותר מגופו, u'mechabda yoter m'gufo, and respects her even more than himself,
and respect here is normally explained in the same way כיבוד אם
kibbud em is about issues relating to taking care of the person's
physical needs like clothing and dressing and feeding and so on but
seems to be also in a broader context as well. והמדריך בניו
ובנותיו בדרך ישרה, ve'hamadrich banav u'venotav b'derech yeshara,
and somebody who instructs his children to go on the right path,
והמשיאן סמוך לפרקן, ve'hamassian samuch l'pirkan, and marries them off near to
their age of
maturity, עליו הכתוב אומר, alav hakatuv omer, regarding him the verse says,
וידעת כי שלום אהלך, v'yadata ki shalom ohalecha, you will know that
your tent will be in peace,
ופקדת נוך ולא תחטא, u'fakadta navecha v'lo techeta, which was the end
of the verse before. So here of course what's added is the
children and
educating them on the right moral path and marrying them off while
they're young close to the age of maturity so that they're married
once when they're sexually mature and that they don't sin is apparently
the point, which is interesting here that you have even the idea
of marrying off a young boy while he is quite young. All
right, then the גמרא Gemara says like this, but also the important
point about אוהב אשתו כגופו ומכבדה יותר מגופו, ohev ishto k'gufo u'mechabda
yoter m'gufo, speaking about the husband's obligations in terms of his not
just other obligations which we know שאר כסות ועונה, shear kesut v'onah,
which will be a whole discussion on מסכת כתובות, Masechet Ketubot, but
here in terms of the basic type of interpersonal and ways of
and the nature of the relationship.
האוהב את שכניו, ha'ohev et shechenav, one who loves his neighbors, ומקרב
את קרוביו, ve'hamakarev et kerovav, a nice phrase there, draws his relatives
close, acknowledging that they're not always close,
והנושא את בת אחותו, ve'hanosei et bat achoto, who marries his niece.
There's a question whether it's specifically his sister's daughter or even his
brother's
daughter. והמלווה סלע לעני בשעת דוחקו, ve'hamalveh sela l'ani b'shat dochko, and
somebody who lends money to a poor person when he's in particularly
a time of need, עליו הכתוב אומר: alav hakatuv omer: אז תקרא
וה' יענה תשוע ויאמר הנני. az tikra v'Hashem ya'aneh tishva v'yomar hineni.
Then you will call out and God will answer, you will what?
תשווע, tishva, I know, but the ו vav is in the wrong
place twice here anyway. Anyway, you will okay, and God will say
"here I am." So because and as רש"י Rashi points out because
beforehand it says כי תראה ערום וכיסיתו ומבשרך לא תתעלם, ki tireh
arom v'chisito u'mibesarcha lo titalem, so or אל תתעלם? al titalam? So
you will see a naked person and dress him, so that's מלווה
לעני בשעת דוחקו, malveh l'ani b'shat dochko, and not hiding from your
flesh is taking care of your relatives and marrying your niece and
so on. Okay, moving on. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, now
we're back to listing of the question about the value of being
married, or the value of a wife. אמר רבי אלעזר: Amar Rabbi
Elazar: כל אדם שאין לו אשה אינו אדם, kol adam she'ein lo
isha eino adam, any person without a woman is not any man
obviously without a wife is not a man, שנאמר: shenemar: זכר ונקבה
בראם ויקרא שמם אדם, zachar u'nekeva bera'am vayikra shemam Adam,
their name was Adam, only when they were both male and female
together. So this is obviously very close reflecting the פסוקים psukim in
בראשית Bereishit which is clearly the message of בראשית, Bereishit, that it
creates that sense of being one and of wholeness. ואמר רבי אלעזר,
Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar, Rabbi Elazar also said, כל אדם שאין לו קרקע
אינו אדם. kol adam she'ein lo karka eino adam. Now this of
course takes it away from the uniqueness of marriage: any person without
land is not a real person.
So now that makes you think, wonder if he means something different
when he says כל שאינו אשה אינו אדם kol she-eino isha eino
adam and I saw somebody Sattlow who wrote a book on marriage
in Jewish antiquity and he looks at these passages, I mean a
lot of people have looked at these passages, and he wants to
claim if I remember correctly that Rebbe Elazar's point is more about
a person's societal standing, that having, you know, having a house and
being married is what you need to be sort of recognized as
a person within society. So that's how he wants to sort of
combine the two. That's not some existential statement like, you know, it's
not good, לא טוב היות, lo tov heyot, it makes you complete,
it sort of it makes you a person in society. That's the
way he wanted to read what this Gemara's getting at. Yes, Charlie.
In the United States for a long time you had to be
a real property owner to be able to...
Well right, property we know, the point is, yes, that's exactly his
point. And then the point is exactly seeing that in terms of
being married. Look, it's true now in a lot of, you know,
Jewish communities that people until they're married often are not seen as,
you know, as much as integral, you know, members of the community.
I mean I'm not, you know, it's not a good thing, but
sadly that happens sometimes. So that's how he's sort of reading this.
Okay, so what does the Gemara say?
ואמר רבי אלעזר מאי דכתיב, v'amar Rebbe Elazar mai d'chtiv, what's meant
by the verse אעשה לו עזר כנגדו, e'eseh lo ezer k'negdo, I
will make him a helpmate opposite
him? So זכה עזרתו, zacha ozarto, if he merits then the woman
will be to his assistance. לא זכה כנגדו, lo zacha k'negdo, if
he doesn't merit,
then it'll be opposing him.
ואיכא דאמרי, v'ika d'amri, some say, רבי אלעזר רמי, Rebbe Elazar rami,
he showed a contradiction. כתיב כנגדו, ktiv k'negdo, opposite him, וקרינן כנגדו.
v'karinan k'nigdo. Now what does he, I don't know what it means
וקרינן כנגדו, v'karinan k'nigdo, but anyway let's see what the drasha is.
And we say זכה כנגדו, zacha k'negdo, לא זכה מנגדתו. lo zacha
minagdato. So if he merits then it's meet opposite him like, you
know, meet for him, appropriate for him. If he doesn't merit, so
this is the Aramaic word מנגדתו minagdato which means lash, she lashes
him. Okay, so אשכחיה רבי יוסי לאליהו, ashkechei Rebbe Yossi l'Eliyahu, Rebbe
Yossi found Eliyahu. אמר ליה, amar lei, כתיב אעשה לו עזר, ktiv
e'eseh lo ezer, so it says I will make him a helpmate.
במה אשה עוזרת לאדם, bameh isha ozeret l'adam, how does a woman
help a man? What type of question is this? אמר ליה, amar
lei, so he said to him, אדם מביא חטים, adam meivi chitim,
when a man brings home wheat from the
field, חטים כוסס, chitim koses, does he chew wheat? פשתן, pishtan, if
he brings home
flax, פשתן לובש, pishtan loveshi, does he wear the flax? נמצאת מאירה
עיניו ומעמידתו על רגליו. nimtzeit me'ira einav u'ma'amidato al raglav. So what
does she do? She grinds the wheat into flour and makes it
into bread, she beats the flax, makes it into linen, makes clothes
out of it. נמצאת מאירה עיניו ומעמידתו על רגליו. nimtzeit me'ira einav
u'ma'amidato al raglav. So the woman makes man stand on his... light
up his eyes and stand on his legs. Again, very much in
sort of the very sort of
materialistic, you know, material physical ways and sort of putting the woman
in the, you know, in the kitchen or in the, I don't
know...
Exactly.
All right. So it certainly very clear here about not all these
are exactly our modern ways of seeing things. ואמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar
Rebbe Elazar, said Rebbe Elazar, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by
the verse זאת הפעם עצם מעצמי ובשר מבשרי, zot hapa'am etzem me'atzami
u'vasar mibsari, this time bone of my bone, flesh of my flesh?
מלמד שבא אדם על כל בהמה וחיה, melamed sheba adam al kol
behema v'chaya, man had sex with all animals, ולא נתקררה דעתו, v'lo
nitkarera da'ato, and he did not feel, his mind wasn't put at
ease, עד שבא על חוה, ad sheba al Chava, until he had
sex with Chava and then he felt, oh this is like my,
you know, my own species. Again, why exactly it's reading it that
way because it's trying to understand what made him sort of realize
was just seeing her? So anyway. All right.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar Rebbe Elazar, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant
by the verse ונברכו בך כל משפחות האדמה? v'nivrechu becha kol mishpachot
ha'adamah? So now we're just a string of statements from Rebbe Elazar.
אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא לאברהם, amar lei HaKadosh Baruch Hu l'Avraham,
God said to Avraham, שתי ברכות טובות יש לי להבריך בך. shtei
brachot tovot yesh li l'havrich becha. So here
it's a little play on words not just blessing, ונברכו, v'nivrechu, but
הברכה havracha which is to graft, to graft like a branch of
a tree onto another tree. I have two blessings or, you know,
two graftings to graft onto you. רות המואביה, Rut HaMoaviya, Ruth from
the Moabite, ונעמה העמונית, v'Na'amah HaAmonit, and Na'amah from the Ammonite. כל
משפחות האדמה. kol mishpachot ha'adamah. So anyway
I am going to graft these onto you and obviously you'll be
very blessed. From you will come David and from Ruth will come
David, from Na'amah will come, you know, also children from the
royal... from the greatest kings. So that is the blessing. So which
is an important thing to say in the middle of יבמות Yevamot
because we're going to see later, obviously we've already seen some indications
about בת גרים bat gerim and then גרים gerim and, you know,
different attitudes about like pure lineage and non-pure lineage and here the
גמרא Gemara דווקא davka is saying look at this wonderful blessing that,
you know, a little bit getting a little bit from outside of
our own gene pool here. Okay, so
ונברכו... v'nivrechu... כל משפחות האדמה, kol mishpachot ha'adamah, all of the families
of the... land, אפילו משפחות הדרות באדמה, afilu mishpachot hadarot ba'adamah, even
the families that dwell in the land, I presumably it means like
out there in the fields, like not in cities, like some in
way out on the countryside, אין ברכה אלא בשביל ישראל, ein berachah
ela bishvil Yisrael, all their blessing derives from Israel. כל גויי הארץ,
kol goyei ha'aretz, אפילו, afilu, all the nations of the land, אפילו
ספינות הבאות מגליא לאספמיא, afilu sefinot haba'ot migalya le'aspamya, even the ships
that are going from גליא Galya wherever that is, Gaul, I don't
know, Gaul now. Gaul? Oh, Gaul! Oh, Gaul to Spain. They're totally
distant from our land and they're basically not even on the land,
they're on the sea. אינן מתברכות אלא בשביל ישראל, einan mitbarechot ela
bishvil Yisrael, all their blessing is because of Israel. In the time
of the גמרא? Gemara?
Yeah, there's actually a Rabbi in ירושלמי Yerushalmi from Gaul.
Really? Okay.
There you go.
All right. ואמר רבי אלעזר, ve'amar Rabbi Elazar, עתידין כל בעלי אומנות
שיעמדו על הקרקע, atidin kol ba'alei umanut sheya'amdu al hakarka, all different
craftspeople will eventually stand on the land, which presumably means will also
become working in agriculture, will be farmers. שנאמר, shenemar, as the verse
says, וירדו מאניותיהם כל תופשי משוט מלחים, veyardu me'oniyotayhem kol tofsei mashot
malachim, מלחים? malachin? What?
מלחים. malachim. Thank you. כל חובלי הים על הארץ יעמדו. kol chovlei
hayam al ha'aretz ya'amdu. So
all those that sort of deal with the sail and the seamen
will all go down onto the land. ואמר רבי אלעזר, ve'amar Rabbi
Elazar, אין לך אומנות פחותה מן הקרקע. ein lecha umanut pechutah min
hakarka.
Now, interestingly, you would think that if in the future they'll leave
their other professions and go to the land, you would think that
that's a good thing, but now he's actually saying that it's a
bad thing. Right, is the point that like maybe the point is
exactly that, all the non-Jews will be the farmers so that we
can I don't know, learn תורה Torah or something? But now we
get into, for a while it was just an interesting digression or
an interesting string of statements of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, but now
we're going to get into an interesting little focus on discussing the
value or the good or the bad of working the land. So
let's take a look. And then while we're doing it, I want
you to remember the earlier statement of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that
said anybody who's not married, meaning any man who's not married or
doesn't have land, is not a man.
So we're going to hang on to
something about having someone to work it for you. Right, exactly. So
let's take a look. So he says, ואמר רבי אלעזר, ve'amar Rabbi
Elazar, אין לך אומנות פחותה מן הקרקע, ein lecha umanut pechutah min
hakarka, there is no craft, there is no profession that is more
lowly than working the land. שנאמר, shenemar, וירדו, veyardu, they'll have to
descend from their professions, not just descend from their boats. רבי אלעזר
חזיה לההיא ארעא דשדי בה כרבא לפותיה.
Rabbi Elazar chazya
le'hahi
ara deshadi bei karva lefutya.
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar saw a certain plot of land that there
was a furrow or otherwise read as a cabbage that was being
planted to its width. אמר לה, amar lah, he said to the
land apparently, אי תשדי לאורכך הפוכי בעיסקא טב מינך. ei tishdi le'orchach
hapuchi be'iska tav minach. If you have it going lengthwise,
it's better to be involved in business than to worry about planting
the land. רב על לביני שיבלי. Rav al beveini shivlei. רב Rav
went between the stalks of grain. חזינהו דקא נייפי, chazinhu deka nayfi,
he saw that they were blowing in the wind. אמר להו, amar
lehu, he said to them, אי נייאפי איתנופי הפוכי בעיסקא טב מינכו.
ei nayafi itnufi hapuchi be'iska tav minchu. If you want to blow,
wave in the wind, wave in the wind, but nevertheless
it's much better to just go be involved in business. אמר רבא,
amar Rava,
so we thought that was only in the time of the ראשונים,
Rishonim, but apparently already in the time of the גמרא Gemara it
was better to be involved in business than to be a farmer.
אמר רבא, amar Rava,
מאה זוזי בעיסקא, me'ah zuzei be'iska, if you invest a hundred זוז
zuz in business, כל יומא בשרא וחמרא, kol yoma bisra vechamra, every
day you'll be able to eat meat and drink wine. מאה זוזי
בארעא, me'ah zuzei be'ara, if you invest a hundred זוז zuz in
land and in the, you know, not real estate, but in farming,
מלחא וחפורא, milcha vechafura,
you'll eat vegetables with salt. ולא עוד אלא מגניא ליה אארעא, velo
od ela maganya leh a'ara,
you'll have to sleep on the land to protect the crops, ורמיא
ליה תיגרי, uramya leh tigrei, and you'll get into fights with people,
so it's better to be a businessman. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav
Papa, זרע ולא תזבין. zara velo tazbin.
Now here he says something that seems to be an opposite voice,
plant rather than purchasing. So if you want to get like wheat
or whatever, plant your own wheat, don't go ahead and purchase it.
אף על גב דכי הדדי נינהו, af al gav dechi hadadei ninhu,
even if, what do you mean, it costs the same to buy
flour in the store as it does to plant the wheat and
to turn it into flour, הני מברכי, hani mevarchei, no, the work
of your own hands is blessed, so rather produce it on your
own rather than go buy it in the store. זבין ולא תזור.
zabin velo tazor.
Now רש"י Rashi reads this as, there's a question how רש"י Rashi
goes to read this, רש"י Rashi reads this as if you sell
things before, sell your own property before,
not real estate, sell your objects before you become poor. But... הני
מילי בסטרקא, Hani milei bistarka, that's only like selling things like mats
or other types of things, but גלימא, gelima, to sell your clothes,
לא, lo, לא מסתרימלי. lo mistramlei. You, no,
you wouldn't sell it because we'd be afraid that you wouldn't be
able to buy something that would fit you, that would be as
appropriate for you. That's how רש״י Rashi is, which is a little
funny, doesn't exactly fit the earlier theme. תוספות Tosafot reads it as
you should purchase, similar before where it says plant and don't purchase,
here saying purchase and don't—actually, תוספות's Tosafot גרסא girsa is something else,
purchase—no, he says תיזול, tizol, but it means don't weave. While
you should plant your own food, you should purchase your own clothes,
but don't weave your own clothes, okay? But that's only in terms
of like other things, mats and the other thing, but if it's
actually something like a cloak, that you might want to weave yourself
so that it fits you, custom tailor, exactly. Anyway, so this idea
where he says plant for yourself, is that contradicting what the גמרא
Gemara said before where it's sort of deriding the value of saying
how difficult it is to be a farmer?
אמר אלעזר בר אבינא, Amar Elazar bar Avina, אין פורענויות באות לעולם
אלא בשביל ישראל. ein puraniyot ba'ot la'olam ella bishvil Yisrael. Bad things
happen to the world for the sake of Israel, which is
interesting, שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, הכרתי גוים נשמו פינותם, hikratti
goyim nashammu pinnotam, I have I have cut off nations, their corners
have been desolate, החרבתי חוצותם, hecherevti chutzotam, I have laid waste to
their, you know, to their field or courtyards, וכתיב, u-chtiv, אמרתי אך
תראי אותי תקחי מוסר, amarti ach tir'i oti tikchi musar, lest I
I said perhaps you will fear me and take heed. So therefore,
bad things happening to the whole world just that you ישראל Yisrael
should take heed. רב, Rav, alright, I don't know what to make
with that. רב, Rav, I don't know what exactly to do in
here either. רב הוי מיפטר מרבי חייא, Rav hava miptar mi-Rabbi Chiyya,
רב Rav was departing from רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiyya. אמר ליה, Amar
leih, רחמנא ליצלן ממידי דקשי ממותא. Rachamana litzlan mimmidi de-kashi mimota. So
he said to him, let God save us from something that is
worse than death, a fate worse than death. ואיכא מידי דקשי ממותא?
Ve-ika middi de-kashi mimota? Is there something worse than death? He thought
to himself. נפק דק ואשכח, Nafak dak ve-ashkach, he went, he looked
and he found the פסוק, pasuk, ומוצא אני מר ממות את האשה.
u-motze ani mar mimmavet et ha-ishah. I find more difficult than death
the woman אשר היא מצודות וחרמים asher hi metzodot u-charamim etc. So
now we get to a גמרא Gemara which is, you know, again,
all written by men talking about wives. So beforehand it was talking
about why it's good to be married from the man's perspective, sometimes
intrinsic, sometimes instrumental, but you know, but now we get to the,
and you know, and it's a talk about taking care of a
wife's sexual needs and being aware of the man being aware, but
again, it was all still very much from the man's perspective. And
now we're getting to hearing men say why it's why sometimes it's
hard to be married and their attitude towards, you know, a mixed
attitude. So let's take a look. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. רב הוי קא מצטרא ליה דביתהו. Rav hava ka metzatra
leih devitehu. רב's Rav wife was giving him a very hard time.
Which one?
I assume he had a lot of wives one at a time.
Oh, yeah. Was רב Rav married to...
wasn't he married to רב חייא's Rav Chiyya
sister? Or daughter?
What does it say there?
It says רב חייא Rav Chiyya was his חביבא chaviva and also
his uncle.
רב חייא Rav Chiyya was his uncle and... oh no, so he
wasn't married. No, no. What? No, no. Okay, anyway, because here he
is departing from רב חייא. Rav Chiyya. So anyway, so he was
the one that said to anyway he said to רב חייא Rav
Chiyya I read more difficult than death. So now we see that
he's now we're going to see what the story was that was
behind why he said that. רב הוי קא מצטרא ליה דביתהו. Rav
hava ka metzatra leih devitehu. רב's Rav wife gave him, was caused
him a lot of anguish.
כי אמר לה, Ki amar lah, עבדי לי טלופחי, avdi li tluphi,
make for me lentils, עבדה ליה חמצי. avda leih chimtzi. She made
for him some type of a like a pickled brine dish. חמצי...
Chimtzi... P what? Peas for the first one? טלופחי, Tluphi, what does
it say, חמצי?
chimtzi? It says very similar, which is very similar to lentils.
No, okay, wait, חמצי chimtzi is the one that she did instead
of lentils? Yeah. Alright, not a big difference then. חמצי, Chimtzi, I
also in my mind חמוצים, chamutzim, I assumed it meant, anyway. עבדה
ליה טלופחי. Avda leih tluphi. Anyway, she would switch them on him.
כי גדל חייא בריה, Ki gdal Chiyya bereih, when חייא Chiyya his
son grew up, אפיך לה. afich lah. So and then he sold,
he told חייא, Chiyya, he said tell your mom to make me
טלופחי, tluphi, so חייא Chiyya figured out what was going on, so
he said to the mother make daddy חמצי. chimtzi. So in the
end he got what he, you know, what he wanted. So אפיך
לה. afich lah. אמר ליה, Amar leih, so then when he got
his food
given to him he said oh look this is what I asked
for! So he said to his son, איעליא לך אימך. i-alya lach
imach. So your mother has now, you know, some better by you,
like your mother is now improved. Your mother's improved. אמר ליה, Amar
leih, he said so the son said to the father no, אנא
הוא דקאפיכנא לה. ana hu de-ka-afichna lah. I reversed it for her
so that you got ultimately what you, you know, what you wanted.
So אמר ליה, Amar leih, he said to him, היינו דאמרי אינשי,
hainu de-amri inshi, that's what people say, דנפיק מינך טעמא מלפך. de-nafik
minach ta'ama malfach. The one that comes from you will teach you,
you know, advice, will give you, will teach you reason. You learn
from your kids. Yeah. אף על גב, Af al gav, I don't
know, but nevertheless even though that was a brilliant idea, את לא
תעביד הכי, at lo ta'avid hachi, don't do that, שנאמר, shene'emar, למדו
לשונם דבר שקר העוו
נלאו. limdu leshonam daber sheker ha'avu nil'u. So teach you should not
be teaching your tongues
to speak falsehood.
Okay? So that was the story with his wife. Now you know,
again you read this
and I mean I read this as a man and I'm sort
of saying like okay, it's very nice like, you know, to hear
how husbands are complaining about their wives, when do we get to
hear how wives are complaining about their husbands? But okay, nevertheless, you
know, that was just my general approach but you know obviously I
said okay whatever, so רב Rav had a bad wife, some plenty
of women to have bad husbands. But I then I read this
brilliant
מדרש, Midrash, like you know it's one of the things they do
now are contemporary מדרשים, Midrashim, I'm just looking to pull it up
here because I I put it on my iPhone, by
רבקה לוביץ, Rivkah Lubitch, who wrote this, who wrote and there's a
collection called, I forget what
it's called. גמרא. Gemara. So I'll just quote, I'll get to, I
want to read you the part that she wrote. Okay, here's what
she wrote. This is her part two of the גמרא. Gemara.
Wait, so she just reimagined it?
Yeah, or she wrote like, she wrote the woman's perspective on this.
Okay, so it says like this. Yeah, it says: לא משום שהפעמים
היה אומר לה רב שיקדים לבוא מבית המדרש מבעוד יום והיה בא
אחרי צאת הכוכבים. Lo mishum sheha-peamim hayah omer lah Rav sheyakdim lavo
mi-beit ha-midrash mi-be'od yom ve-hayah ba acharei tzeit ha-kochavim. Why did she
do this? Not because רב Rav would sometimes tell her he's going
to come home early and he would come from the בית מדרש
beit midrash and he would come home after like it got very
dark. והייתה יושבת אשתו בעליבותא ומצפה לו עד שהיה מתעורר עליה רוגזא
וכעסא. Ve-hayetah yoshevet ishto be-alivuta u-metzapa lo ad she-hayah mitorer aleiha rugza
ve-ka-asa. So
and and she would be sitting there and feeling like and you
know, distraught and looking for her until you know, until she would
finally and then she'd start getting you know, really angry and upset.
That's not why she would do this. ופעמים שהיה אומר לה שיאחר
לבוא מבית המדרש והיה מקדים לבוא לפני זמנו. U-feamim she-hayah omer lah
she-ye'acher lavo mi-beit ha-midrash ve-hayah makdim lavo lifnei zemano. And sometimes he'd
say he'd come home late and instead he'd come home early. והייתה
אשתו מתרוצצת אנה ואנה להתקין, le-hatkin, I'm sorry, just losing, להתקין לו
סעודתו, le-hatkin lo se'udato, and then she'd have to be running like
crazy in order to prepare the meal. That's not why she did
this. ולא משום, Ve-lo mishum, and not because שפעמים היה רומז לה
שיקבעו סעודתם יחדיו. she-peamim hayah romez lah she-yikbeu se'udatam yachdav.
Sometimes he would indicate that they'd want to have a private meal
together. והיה בא מבית המדרש עם תלמידים לרוב, Ve-hayah ba mi-beit ha-midrash
im talmidim la-rov, and then at night he'd come home with all
of his students. והיו יושבים ואוכלים ונהנים וזו עמלה להגיש לכולם, Ve-hayu
yoshvim ve-ochlim ve-nehenim ve-zu amela le-hagish le-kulam, and they'd be eating and
drinking and she'd be working to feed them all. והם מנעימים פיהם
בדברי חכמה וחידוד, Ve-hem man'imim pihem be-divrei chochma ve-chidud, and they'd be
all talking in תורה. Torah. ובסוף מברכים את השם. U-ve-sof me-varchim et
ha-Shem. And then they'd give bless God. And the גמרא, Gemara, that's
not why. ופעמים היה אומר לה שיביא אורחים לסעודה. U-feamim hayah omer
lah she-yavi orchim li-se'udah. Sometimes he'd tell her that he'd bring guests.
והייתה עומדת
ומתקנת סעודה יפה, Ve-hayetah omedet u-metakenet se'udah yafah, and she'd make a
beautiful meal. ובסוף, U-ve-sof, and in the end, hold on, I think
you see where this is going, okay, ובסוף היה בא בגפו, u-ve-sof
hayah ba be-gapo, and sometimes he'd come alone. No, it was not
because of any of that. אלא משום שכשידע רב שבישלה אשתו חמיצי,
Ela
mishum
she-kesheyada Rav she-bishla ishto chimtzi, but when רב Rav knew that his
wife had cooked חמיצי, chimtzi, היה מבקש טלוסחי, hayah me-vakesh tlushchi,
all of a sudden he wanted טלוסחי. tlushchi. וכשהיה יודע שבישלה טלוסחי
היה מבקש חמיצי, U-cheshehayah yodea she-bishla tlushchi hayah me-vakesh chimtzi, and when
she wanted טלוסחי, tlushchi, that's when he decided to ask for חמיצי.
chimtzi. וזו שתקה ולא אמרה לו דבר. Ve-zu shatka ve-lo amra lo
davar. And she, what did she do? She was quiet and she
didn't say anything to him. רק הגישה לו את מה שהיה מתוקן
בסיר. Rak hegisha lo et mah she-hayah metukan ba-sir. She just gave
him what she had already prepared. ולא היה יודע האיש ההוא למה
ועל מה עושה לו כך... והיא לא הייתה יודעת האישה האומללה על
מה ולמה עושה לה כך בעלה. Ve-hi lo hayetah yoda'at ha-isha ha-umlala
al mah ve-lama oseh lah kach ba'alah. And she didn't know, this
poor woman, why her husband was treating her like this. הלא הוא
כל עולמה וכל עמלה, Halo hu kol olamah ve-chol amalah, isn't he
her whole world and everything she works for? וכך היתה מרה כל
הימים, Ve-kach hayetah mara kol ha-yamim, she was bitter her whole
life. וכמעט שביקשה נפשה למות, Ve-kim'at she-biksha nafsha la-mut, and it's for
this that they said, her friend said to her: ומוצא אני מר
ממות את האשה. U-motzei ani mar mi-mavet et ha-ishah. Wow. So
really gives you a sense of what it would look like, the
same story from a very different perspective.
Alright, so we'll move on now in the גמרא. Gemara. But with
that in mind, I think now we're prepared to read the rest
of the story in the גמרא. Gemara. So אמר ליה רב, Amar
lei Rav, so that was רב. Rav. רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, now
רבי חייא הוה קא מצערא ליה דביתהו, Rabbi Chiya havah ka metzaara
lei devitehu,
his wife was giving him a hard time. כי הוה משכח מידי,
Ki havah meshakach midi, but nevertheless when he found a nice little
thing in the marketplace, צייר ליה בסודרא, tzayer lei be-sudara, he wrapped
it in his handkerchief to bring her a nice piece of fruit,
a nice piece of jewelry or something to bring it to her.
אמר ליה רב, Amar lei Rav, so רב Rav said to him,
והא קא מצערא ליה למר, Ve-ha ka metzaara lei le-mar, but she
causes you such anguish. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to
him, דיינו, Dayeinu, it's enough for us שמגדלות בנינו ומצילות אותנו מן
החטא, she-megadlot baneinu u-matziylot otanu min ha-chet,
that they raise our children and they save us from sexual sin.
So even though however much hard time we have from our wives,
we have to be appreciative. Okay, מקרי ליה רב יהודה לרב יצחק.
Makrei lei Rav Yehuda le-Rav Yitzchak. By the way, Satlow says that
it's also finds it interesting the shift from the Tannaitic material where
it's all about praising marriage for whatever different reasons it is and
this material, which I don't think he comments on again the fact
that it's totally from the man's perspective, but he does comment on
the fact that it's very just realistic that not all marriages are
so wonderful and sometimes marriages are very difficult and people
whatever you know, question is what attitude do you bring to them
and you stay in the marriage, you get out of the marriage
and so on. מקרי ליה רב יהודה לרב יצחק בריה. Makrei lei
Rav Yehuda le-Rav Yitzchak bireih. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda read to
רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak his son the following פסוק: pasuk: ומוצא אני
מר ממות את האשה. U-motzei ani mar mi-mavet et ha-ishah. I find
more bitter than death the woman. אמר ליה כגון מאן, Amar lei
kegon man, what would be an example of this? So he said,
כגון אמך, Kegon imecha, like your mother. So one wonders. was like
the story before also about רב Rav and his son, which is
like, you know, how good is having these conversations with one's children
about their respect for one's parents? But anyway, why didn't any of
these people get divorced?
Well, we're going to get to that. Okay, ואמרת ליה רב יהודה
לרב יצחק בריה, ve-amarta lei Rav Yehuda le-Rav Yitzchak brei, but one
minute, didn't רב יהודה Rav Yehuda teach רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak his
son, אין אדם מוצא קורת רוח אלא מאשתו ראשונה, ein adam motze
korat ruach ela me-ishto rishona, a man does not find like satisfaction
of spirit except from his first wife, שנאמר יהי מקורך ברוך, shenemar
yehi mekorecha baruch, your source will be blessed, meaning the מקור mekor
meaning קורת רוח, korat ruach, ושמח מאשת נעוריך, u-smach me-eshet neurecha, or
and rejoice from the wife of your of your youth. ואמר ליה,
ve-amar lei, and he said to him, כגון מאן? kegon man? Who
would be an example of this? And he said, כגון אמך, kegon
imcha, like your mother. So what is it? Was his mother the
one that gave him, you know, a deep sense of satisfaction or
מר ממות? mar mi-mavet? So the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף תקיפא ואבורי
מיאבורי במילי. matkif takifa ve-avurei mi-avurei be-milei.
Yeah,
she would get very angry but then she could be pacified and
calm down with some nice words. So there was a it was
mixed. You'd have very hard times sometimes with his wife, but also
was very a lot of very positive, which is like a lot
of marriages. It's not all one or the other. היכי דמי אשה
רעה? heichi dami isha ra'a? So now that was mixed. Now, or
either mixed because it genuinely was mixed or the story before by
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, which is even if it is bad you
have to sort of at the, you know, in terms of the
relationship level, but but you know, still be appreciative of what the
other person does in the marriage. So now we get to sort
of the more of an of a black and white. What would
be an example of a bad wife? היכי דמי אשה רעה? heichi
dami isha ra'a? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, מקשטה ליה תכא ומקשטה ליה
פומא. mekashta lei taka u-mekashta lei puma. She fixes the the dish
and she prepares the dish at the same time she's preparing her
mouth
to yell
at you to yell at the husband while she she makes his
meals and she's getting ready to berate him during the meal. רבא
אמר מקשטה ליה תכא, Rava amar mekashta lei taka, she prepares the
meal, the dish, ומהדרה ליה גבא, u-mahadra lei gava, and she turns
her back her back to him. So she like you know, she
ignores him during the meal, she shuns him. אמר רבי חמא בר
חנינא, amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina, כיון שנשא אדם אשה, keivan she-nasa
adam isha, עונותיו מתפקקים. avonotav mitpakkekim.
When a man so now more positive, when a man marries a
woman his sins are
forgiven.
Interesting word מתפקקים. mitpakkekim.
Yeah, רש"י Rashi says it means like covered up or buried or
sealed, based on the פסוק pasuk שנאמר מצא אשה מצא טוב ויפק
רצון מה' shenemar matza isha matza tov ve-yaphek ratzon me-Hashem to derive
desire from God. So somehow it means to like close up, seal
up the sins, I don't know. ומה במערבא, u-ma be-ma'arava, in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, כי נסיב איניש איתתא, ki nasiv inish iteta,
when a man would marry a woman, אמרי ליה הכי, amrei lei
hachi, they'd say they'd say to him, מצא או מוצא? matza o
motze? So how's your wife? Is she a מצא matza or a
מוצא? motze? The way that means, מצא דכתיב מצא אשה מצא טוב,
matza de-chtiv matza isha matza tov, when one finds one finds good,
or מוצא דכתיב ומוצא אני מר ממות את האשה. motze de-chtiv u-motze
ani mar mi-mavet et ha-isha. So it would be this ingenious way
of asking how's the marriage workin' out, how things goin', how's the
marriage workin' out? But again, also reflecting the idea, you know, that
we don't live in this idealized world where marriages are always good,
recognizing that
sometimes it's mixed, sometimes it's good, sometimes it's you know, sometimes it's
bad. I heard a beautiful דרשה drasha on this once though which
which was
the
which was that the question wasn't about the woman, the question was
about the man, which is מצא או מוצא? matza o motze? What
type of a person are you? Are you a מצא, matza, somebody
when you find something you're happy, you found something, you have מציאה,
metzia, you know, you stop looking. So then it's מצא אשה מצא
טוב. matza isha matza tov. Or are you a מוצא, motze, that
even after you've found, you're looking around, maybe I could've got something
better, maybe there's someone else out there? Then ומוצא אני מר ממות
את האשה. u-motze ani mar mi-mavet et ha-isha. Then you're never going
to be happy. That was a very nice דרשה. drasha. Okay. Okay.
אמר
רבא אשה רעה מצוה לגרשה.
amar Rava
isha ra'a mitzvah le-garsha. So now's the question about like living in
though you know do do you stay married or or not? You
know, and as we know this is a big issue because in
terms of issues of עגונה aguna that some בתי דין batei din
are very resistant to or that's even putting it lightly, you know,
you know, refuse to do anything in terms of trying to to
get a divorce because it's with an assumption that it's always better
to be married. You know, under the banner of שלום בית, shalom
bayit, meaning it's always better to be married. שלום. shalom. Yeah, exactly.
So anyway, so רבא Rava says if if a man has a
bad wife but we might say if the marriage is bad, מצוה
לגרשה, mitzvah le-garsha, it's a mitzvah to divorce her,
דכתיב גרש לץ ויצא מדון וישבות דין וקלון. de-chtiv garesh letz ve-yeitzei
madon ve-yishbot din ve-kalon. Drive out the mocker and get rid of
the of the of the fight and the fighting and the cursing
will cease. ואמר רבא הא אשה רעה וכתובתה מרובה. ve-amar Rava ha
isha ra'a u-chtuvata meruba. So let's say a man has a bad
wife but she has a large כתובה ketubah and he can't afford
to
divorce
her. So marry another wife and that'll help because the fact that
she's got a little competition there, that'll change things. You got to
hope that they don't join beat you into exactly. דאמרי אינשי *Da’amri
inshi*, as people say, בחברתא ולא בסילתא *be-chavarta v’lo b’silta*, better to
sort of change somebody’s behavior through a friend, meaning through a competitor,
and not with a thorn. Okay, so just bringing some competition into
the marriage, that’ll do a lot of good. ואמר רבא *V’amar Rava*,
קשה אשה רעה כיום סגריר *Kasheh isha ra’ah k’yom sagrir*. A bad
wife is as bad as like a heavy stormy day. שנאמר shene'emar
*She-ne’emar*, דלף טורד ביום סגריר ואשת מדיינים נשתווה *Delef tored b’yom sagrir
v’eshes midyanim nishtaveh*. That like an unrelenting rain on a stormy day
and a woman who, a contentious woman are equated. ואמר רבא *V’amar
Rava*, בא וראה כמה טובה אשה טובה וכמה רעה אשה רעה *Bo
u’re’ei kamah tovah isha tovah v’kamah ra’ah isha ra’ah*. Come see how
good is a good wife and how bad is a bad wife.
אי בגברא משתעי קרא *Ei
b’gavra mishtai kra*, if it’s literal, מצא אשה מצא טוב *Matza isha
matza tov*, one who finds a wife finds good. כמה טובה אשה
טובה שכתוב משבחה *Kamah tovah isha tovah she-kasuv m’shabc-hah*. So okay, that’s
self-explanatory. Look how good a woman is, it says finds woman finds
good. It’s talking about the good of a good wife. אי בתורה
משתעי קרא *Ei b’Torah mishtai kra*, if it’s meant metaphorically that אשה
*isha* here refers to תורה *Torah*, which is a lot of משלי
*Mishlei*, or wisdom at least. So, and means finds Torah finds good.
Nevertheless, כמה טובה אשה טובה שהתורה נמשלה בה *Kamah tovah isha tovah
she-ha-Torah nimshalah bah*. How good is a good wife, that when the
Torah speaks about the greatness of finding Torah, it compares it to
finding a good woman. So either way, whether it’s literal or metaphorical,
it shows you how good it is. כמה רעה אשה רעה דכתיב
ומוצא אני מר ממות את האשה *Kamah ra’ah isha ra’ah dichsiv u’motze
ani mar mimaves es ha-isha*. I find bitterer than death the woman.
אי בגברא משתעי קרא *Ei b’gavra mishtai kra*, כמה רעה אשה רעה
שכתוב מגנה *Kamah ra’ah isha ra’ah she-kasuv m’ganah*. How bad is she,
that the pasuk is going out of the way to speak about
how bad she is. אי בגיהנם משתעי קרא *Ei b’Gehinnom mishtai kra*,
if it’s a metaphor for גיהנם *Gehinnom*, כמה רעה אשה רעה שגיהנם
נמשלה בה *Kamah ra’ah isha ra’ah she-Gehinnom nimshalah bah*. How bad is
she, that she is the metaphor for גיהנם *Gehinnom*. Okay, so again,
playing on the two פסוקים psukim *psukim* of ומוצא אני מר ממות
*U’motze ani mar mimaves* and מצא אשה מצא טוב *Matza isha matza
tov*, and speaking about, you know, again, that there is a wide
range
which look, is true, but of course they never speak about the
wide range of good or bad husbands either. הנני מביא רעה שלא
יוכלו לצאת ממנה *Hineni meivi ra’ah she-lo yuchlu latzes mimena*. Behold I
will bring evil that you will not be able to escape from
it. אמר רב Rav נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה זו אשה רעה
וכתובתה מרובה *Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha zo isha ra’ah
u’kesubasah merubah*. Okay, that is a bad wife with a large כתובה
*kesubah* and can’t escape because, you know, you’re always living together and
there's no way out. נתנני השם בידי לא אוכל קום *Nesannani Hashem
b’yadei lo uchal kum*. God has given me into those that I
cannot stand up among. אמר רב חסדא אמר מר עוקבא בר חייא
זו אשה רעה וכתובתה מרובה *Amar Rav Chisda amar Mar Ukva bar
Chiyya zo isha ra’ah u’kesubasah merubah*. Same idea. It’s a different idea
of I can’t stand up, לא אוכל קום *lo uchal kum*. במערבא
אמרי זו שמזונותיה תלויים בכספה *B’ma’arava amri zo she-mezonoseha teluyim b’chaspa*. There
you go, Mike, point you said before. This is somebody that does
not grow their own food, interesting in terms of reflecting the earlier
issue, and always has to go out and buy food and you
never know whether you will always be able to what you’ll be
able to find food in the market. I mean, that was in
a time when, you know, they, you know, that’s,
we sometimes very much underappreciate what it means to be living in
the plenty of you walk into a supermarket and everything is always
available. I do wonder by the way about בידי לא אוכל קום
*b’yadei lo uchal kum* if it gets back or echoes back to
that גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about מאורת עינינו ומקימת רגלינו *me’iras eineinu u’mekimas
ragleinu*, that the wife sort of, you know, provide, you know, gives,
you know, behind every, you know, whatever, like, you know, gives the
man his standing in society and allows him, you know, takes care
of the things at home to allows him to be, you know,
literally figure, at least figuratively stand up. So seems to be that
that’s the point there, yes.
That quote from איכה *Eicha*, they’re comparing a bad wife to the
Babylonians who burned down the Temple?
What can I tell you. Moving on. Okay. בניך ובנותיך נתונים לעם
אחר *Banecha u’venosecha nesunim l’am acher*. אמר רב חנן בר רבא אמר
רב זו אשת האב *Amar Rav Chanan bar Rava amar Rav zo
eshes ha-av*. That is a stepmother. So בניך ובנותיך נתונים לעם אחר
*Banecha u’venosecha nesunim l’am acher*.
How do you get that?
Because your children are under the authority of somebody else who doesn’t
have the, who’s not their parent, who’s, right? Not so nice to
stepmothers. בגוי נבל naval, אכעיסם *B’goy naval ach’isaim*. I will anger them
with a degenerate nation. אמר רב חנן בר רבא אמר רב זו
אשה רעה וכתובתה מרובה *Amar Rav Chanan bar Rava amar Rav zo
isha ra’ah u’kesubasah merubah*. So, yeah. So again, not exactly sure how
that’s בגוי נבל naval, *b’goy naval*, but anyway. רבי אליעזר אומר אלו
הצדוקים *Rabbi Eliezer omer eilu ha-Tzedukim*. Now, צדוקים *Tzedukim* does not really
make sense, and the original גרסא *girsa* is אלו המינים *eilu ha-minim*.
Does anybody have אלו המינים *eilu ha-minim* in their גמרא gemara *Gemara*?
You have it in Steinsaltz. Okay, so, alright. So that’s okay, so
anyway. Now it might have to do with the idea of, well
we'll take a look: וכן הוא אומר אמר נבל בלבו amar naval
belibo. אין אלקים. So like denying God, which is interesting, because if
the מינים Minim are the are the Christians, then the problem you
would think, you know, the Jewish Christians, which is often who the
מינים Minim are, you would think the problem would be,
you know, too many, not too few. But anyway, but it's certainly
not the God that we believe in. Or, you know, wasn't seen
as to be the same understanding of God.
במתניתא תנא. be-matnita tana. Anyway, it's interesting what they connect with the
word נבל, whether it has to specifically do with the idea of
speaking and discourse, you know, because a lot of the stories about
the מינים Minim have to do with debates between the מינים Minim
and arguing verses and so on, so one wonders if that was
a sense in terms of applying it to a bad wife as
well, the sense about like the type of verbal, you know, lashings
and so on, or debates, you know, and fights. במתניתא תנא be-matnita
tana אלו אנשי ברבריא ואנשי מרטנאי. elu anshei Barbarya ve-anshei Martanai.
So I think it's Barbarians, I don't know what מרטנאי Martanai is.
Berbers? Where's Berber? North African Morocco.
Okay. Mauritania? Berbers and Mauritania? Where's Mauritania? You know, it's
south of Morocco. Oh of course. Okay, so that makes sense, both
places in Africa.
By the way, they were Jews, they were Berber Jews.
Okay, so שמהלכין ערומים בשוק. she-me-halchin arumim ba-shuk. They walk naked in
the marketplace. I assume I hope it doesn't mean totally naked, but
let's just say very, you know, mostly mostly naked. שאין לך משוקץ
ומתועב לפני המקום יותר ממי שמהלך בשוק ערום.
she-ein lecha meshukatz u-metoav lifnei ha-Makom yoter mi-mi she-ma-halech ba-shuk
arum. Okay, so they walk around naked in the marketplace. That's נבל,
not because of what they say but because they act in a
disgusting way. רבי יוחנן אמר אלו חברין. Rabbi Yochanan amar elu Chaverin.
These are חברין. Chaverin. Now חברין Chaverin and not חבר, Chaver, the
word חבר Chaver refers often I think means sometimes like the people
in the type of the בית שני Bayit Sheini that ate their
חולין בטהרה, chulin be-tahara, but it also is a type of a
Persian, Babylonian people that came later to בבל Bavel in the time
of רב and were much more, you know, oppressive, and particularly for,
they did not give any, as opposed to other Babylonian authorities, they
did not give respect to the
תלמידי חכמים.
talmidei chachamim. It's suggested they were Zoroastrian priests as well.
Zoroastrian priests. So that's interesting.
חבארי. Chabarei. חבארי. Chabarei. Okay, that's good to know how to pronounce
it differently. אלו חבארי. elu Chabarei. אמרו ליה לרבי יוחנן amru leh
le-Rabbi Yochanan so they said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אתו
חבראי לבבל atu Chabarai le-Bavel or חבראי לבבל. Chabarai le-Bavel. So they
came to Babylonia. שגא ונפל. shaga ve-nafal. So he collapsed because he
he said this is terrible now, it's going to be bad for
all the rabbis there. אמרו ליה amru leh they said to him,
he's in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they said to him, מקבלי שוחדא.
mekablei shochada. Oh no, but they can be bribed. תריץ ויתיב. taritz
ve-yativ. So then he he like he sat back up. He felt,
you know, he recovered. Because as long as they can be bribed
it's not so bad. גזרו על ג' מפני ג'. gazru al gimel
mipnei gimel. So apparently these חבארין, Chabarim, you know, decreed three edicts
against the Jews of בבל Bavel for because of three sins. על
בשרא. al bisra. So they were not allowed to eat kosher meat.
מפני המתנות. mipnei ha-matanot. This was a punishment back to them, I
assume the Babylonians weren't doing this because of this reason, this is
sort of seen as why it happened in a sort of, you
know, religious reason. Because they did not give the gifts to the
priests from the cows, from the, you know, from the animals that
they slaughtered. So as a result, well there's a whole discussion about,
yeah, מתנות בזמן הזה matanot ba-zman ha-zeh and so on. But it
doesn't, it's not limited to ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. גזרו על המרחצאות מפני הטבילה. gazru al ha-merchatz-ot mipnei
ha-tevila.
They basically prevented them from using the bathhouses because the Jews, and
this is comeuppance because the Jews weren't careful on on going to
the
מקוה. mikveh. Yeah. וקמחטטי שכבי. ve-ka-machtati shichvei. And they exhumed the dead.
And apparently I don't know at least רש''י Rashi says this is
because they believed that the dead couldn't be buried in the earth
that it would impurify the earth and so on.
Zoroastrian, yeah, they take the body and they put the body exposed
to the sky, you know, like on a loft, like down into
a large covered area and they have vultures come and simply just
eat the flesh,
pick the flesh off the skeleton.
Oh my God.
Wow. Okay. So they would exhumed the dead. מפני ששמחים ביום אידם.
mipnei she-smeichim be-yom eidam. Because the Jews would, now this actually seems
to be that the that this was not why God brought it
about, but because but because they were getting back at the Jews,
that the Jews, well it depends how you read יום אידם. yom
eidam. יום אידם yom eidam does it mean bad days, which would
be then that that would be motivating them to pay them back
if the Jews were happy when bad things happened to to the
Zoroastrians, but יום אידם yom eidam in the גמרא gemara sense means
it's like one of those euphemistic phrases, also means like their holidays.
So then it could be that if the Jews, which fits better
in the sense of what we're reading, that if the Jews participated
and rejoiced in the Zoroastrian holidays, so this was now their punishment,
this thing that's brought about. that if the Jews participated and rejoiced
in the Zoroastrian holidays, so this was now their punishment, this thing
that's brought about terrible mourning. שנאמר She'ne'emar, והיתה יד ה' בכם ובאבותיכם.
vahayta yad Hashem bachem uv'avoteichem. The hand of God will be against
you and your fathers. How could it be against your fathers? It's
only in the case of the exhuming of the bodies. אמר רבה
בר שמואל זו חיתוטי שכבי. Amar Rabbah bar Shmuel zu chitutei shichvi.
That's the exhuming of the bodies. דאמר מר בעוון חיים מתים מתחטטים
de'amar mar ba'avon chayim metim mitchatetin because of the sin of those
that are alive, the dead are exhumed. אמר ליה רבה לרב מרי.
Amar lei
Rabbah lerav Mari. כתיב, Ktiv, one verse says לא יאספו ולא יקברו
לדומן על פני האדמה יהיו lo ye'asfu velo yikaveru ledomen al pnei
ha'adama yihiyu and since we're talking about burial, it says they will
not be gathered and will not be buried, they will be left
as like dung on the face of the earth. וכתיב V'chtiv and
the other פסוק pasuk says ונבחר מות מחיים venivchar mavet mechayim that
death will be preferred to life. How could death be preferred to
life? Is this what's going to happen to you in your death?
So again speaking about the tragedy of the body not being buried.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, ונבחר מות לרשעים, venivchar mavet lerasha'im, no it
doesn't mean that death will be preferred to life. It means in
general death it would be is something that the רשעים resha'im should
hope for more, rather to die שלא יחיו בעולם הזה shelo yichyu
ba'olam hazeh rather than to live in this world ויחטאו ויפלו בגיהנום
veyechetu veyipelu bagehinnom and they'll sin and fall into Gehennom. Okay. Now
back to, so that was a little bit of a digression but
about what says אמר נבל בלבו. But back to why. כתוב בספר
בן סירא. Katuv besefer Ben Sira. It's written in the book of
Ben Sira. So on one hand Ben Sira something is supposed to
be one of the ספרים חיצוניים sefarim chitzoniyim we're not supposed to
read, but now the גמרא gemara here says it's written and he
uses the word כתוב, katuv, not, you know, it's written like it's
scripture. Exactly. All right. So I believe you, that's
like the only book from the Persian period that has stuff like
from the fourth century or something like that before the common era.
Really? It's a huge find of manuscripts found in Cairo.
Ben Sira's
like of particular significance for this time period. Interesting. Okay. So let's
take a look. אשה טובה מתנה טובה לבעלה. Isha tova matana tova
leva'alah. A good woman is a good gift to her husband. וכתיב
V'chtiv טובה בחיק יראי אלקים תנתן, tova becheik yerei Elokim tinaten, I'm
sorry, וכתיב V'chtiv here is taken out, this is
actually attributed like this:
אשה טובה מתנה טובה, Isha tova matana tova, a good wife is
a good gift, then it should jump to the words בחיק יראי
אלקים תנתן, becheik yerei Elokim tinaten, will be given into the into
the bosom of the one who fears God. Yeah, right. אשה רעה
צרעת לבעלה, Isha ra'ah tzara'at leva'alah, a bad woman is a plague
to her husband and then the גמרא Gemara inserts מאי תקנתיה? Mai
takantei? What's what if you're stuck? יגרשנה מיד ותתרפא מצרעתו, Yegareshena miyad
vetitraper mitzara'ato, divorce her immediately and be healed from the leprosy. אשה
יפה אשרי בעלה, Isha yafa ashrei ba'alah,
a beautiful woman happy is her husband. מספר ימיו כפליים, Mispar yamav
kiflayim, the number of his days will be doubled. העלם עיניך מאשת
חן, He'alem eineicha me'ishet chen, but hide your eyes from a charming
woman. פן תלכד במצודתה, Pen tilached bimtzudatah, lest you be caught in
her net. אל תטה אצל בעלה, Al tetei etzel ba'alah, do not
attach while she's married, stay away from her, do not incline towards
her husband למסוך עמו יין ושכר limsoch imo yayin veshichar to drink
with him wine and mead. כי בתואר אשה יפה ki beto'ar isha
yafa because in the visage of a beautiful woman רבים הושחתו rabbim
hushchatu many have become have been destroyed ועצומים כל הרוגיה va'atzumim kol
harugeiha and great are all those that she has that she has
you know died literally that she has killed. רבים היו פצעי רוכל,
Rabbim hayu pitzei rochel, great are the wounds of the spice merchant
of the fragrant merchant, right? המרגילים לדבר עבירה hamargilim lidvar aveira which
because the fragrances lead people to sin, right, the perfumes. כניצוץ מבעיר
גחלת Kenitzotz mav'ir gachelet like a spark on a on a coal.
ככלוב מלא עוף Kechluv malei of like a like a bird like
a bird trap filled with birds. כן בתיהם מלאים מרמה ken bateihem
mele'im mirma so their houses are filled with deceit. אל תצר צרת
מחר, Al tetzar tzarat machar, so now moving away from women, do
not weigh about the about the what's going to happen tomorrow, don't
have general like you know anxiety and be all you know and
and and fraught with worries about what what will happen in the
future. כי לא תדע מה ילד יום, ki lo teda mah yeled
yom, you don't know what's going to happen in the next day.
שמא מחר בא ואיננו, shema machar ba ve'einenu, maybe tomorrow will come
and all of your fears won't
materialize, נמצא מצטער על עולם שאינו שלו, nimtza mtzta'er al olam she'eino
shelo, you're worried about a world that's not yours. I know, those
are all Ben Sira, they're all a world that's not yours. I
know, it's a series of quotations, it's not all one verse. Okay.
It's a selection as Dov said so now you don't have to
read it, it's giving you all the good stuff. Okay.
My wife and I have this debate, right? I'm much more the
optimist, she's much more the pessimist. So I say,
so she says, I say, you know, you worry all the time
and like most of it and then and then if it doesn't
come about, you know, what what did you get out of it?
And she says yeah but I'm never like disappointed.
All right. So the גמרא Gemara says all right, so מנע רבים
מתוך
ביתך,
mine'a rabbim
mitoch beitecha,
keep many people from your house, don't have like too many people
in your house, you know, like all these strangers. ולא הכל תביא
לביתך, velo hakol tavi leveitecha, don't have everybody come into your house.
רבים יהיו דורשי שלומך, rabbim yihiyu dorshei shelomecha, many might be those
that are you know seeking after your welfare or trying to be
close, וגלה סוד לאחד מאלף Vegale sod leachad me'alef only reveal your
secrets, only, you know, make, you know, really be close and and
create an intimate connection with one out of a thousand. אמר רבי
אסי. Amar Rabbi Assi.
No word's not gonna come in
any of this, it's just... Correct. Moving on. אין בן דוד בא
Ein Ben David ba back to having kids to bring the Mashiach,
which he basically rejected before because we said halachically, we pasken, we're
not יצא פרו ורבו yotze pru urevu just by having kids; they
have to survive and grow up. But אמר רבי אסי, Amar Rabbi
Assi, אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו כל נשמות שבגוף. Ein Ben
David ba ad sheyichlu kol neshamot shebaguf. Ben David doesn't come until
all the souls are used up. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as it says, כי
רוח מלפני יעטוף ונשמות אני עשיתי. Ki ruach milifnai ya'atof uneshamot ani
asiti. When does the spirit of Mashiach come from me? Because of
the souls that I have made when they get used up. תניא
רבי אליעזר אומר. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer. כל מי שאינו עוסק בפריה
ורביה. Kol mi she'eino osek befirya verivya. Now we have an important
discussion about the value of פרו ורבו, pru urevu, which also gets
to like what its purpose is. Anybody who doesn't involve himself in
פרו ורבו, pru urevu, כאילו שופך דמים, ke'ilu shofech damim, it's like
he spilled blood. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, שופך דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך. Shofech
dam ha'adam ba'adam damo yishafach.
One who spills the blood of a person, by a person his
blood will be spilled. וכתיב בתריה, ואתם פרו ורבו, Uchtiv batrei ve'atem
pru urevu. and you be fruitful and multiply. So it's about human
life. רבי יעקב אומר. Rabbi Yaakov omer. So passively not bringing human
life is almost tantamount to taking human life. רבי יעקב אומר, Rabbi
Yaakov omer, no, כאילו ממעט הדמות. ke'ilu mema'et hadmut.
It's like one decreases the divine presence. שנאמר, כי בצלם אלוהים עשה
את האדם. ki betzelem Elokim asa et ha'adam. Humans are made in
the divine presence. It's not just the blood, it's not just the
physical being, it's about the person as a, being created in צלם
אלוהים. tzelem Elokim. וכתיב בתריה Uchtiv batrei, ואתם פרו ורבו. Ve'atem pru
urevu, בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai omer, כאילו שופך דמים וממעט הדמות.
ke'ilu shofech damim umema'et hadmut.
You get both. שנאמר ואתם פרו ורבו. She'ne'emar ve'atem pru urevu. אמרו
לו לבן עזאי, Amru lo leBen Azzai, they said to Ben Azzai,
יש נאה דורש ונאה מקיים, yesh na'eh doresh vena'eh mekayem, some people,
you know, expound well and fulfill well. נאה מקיים ואין נאה דורש,
na'eh mekayem ve'ein na'eh doresh, or at least do even if they
don't talk about it. ואתה, ve'ata, but you, you're the worst. אתה
נאה דורש ואין נאה מקיים, ata na'eh doresh ve'ein na'eh mekayem, you
talk very nicely but you don't do it. You're not married. אמר
להם בן עזאי, Amar lahem Ben Azzai, Ben Azzai said, ומה אעשה,
uma e'ese, what do you want me to do? שנפשי חשקה בתורה.
shenafshi chashka baTorah. My soul desires Torah. אפשר לעולם שיתקיים על ידי
אחרים. efshar la'olam sheyitkayem al yedei acherim. Other people can get married.
That leads to a whole fascinating discussion, which is, you know, do
you say like somebody learning Torah is, could be exempt from פרו
ורבו? pru urevu? Does this get to an idea that, you know,
maybe if פרו ורבו pru urevu is focused on this idea of,
like we spoke of before, about, like, you know, something about comparing
it to some type of, of like, of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
with some ways compared to פרו ורבו. pru urevu. Is that seen
as some type of a substitute? There's a lot of interesting Torah
on that. But let's just read a little bit more here. תניא
אידך, Tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא. beraita. רבי אליעזר אומר כל
מי שאינו עוסק בפריה ורביה כאילו שופך דמים שנאמר שופך דם האדם
וסמיך ליה ואתם פרו ורבו. Rabbi Eliezer omer kol mi she'eino osek
befirya verivya ke'ilu shofech damim she'ne'emar shofech dam ha'adam usmich lei ve'atem
pru urevu. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר כאילו ממעט הדמות. Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya omer ke'ilu mema'et hadmut. בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai omer,
you both. אמרו לו לבן עזאי יש נאה דורש,
Amru lo leBen Azzai yesh
na'eh doresh, etc.
So basically both. So I guess we won't, I don't know, I
don't know. So alright, I want to just say one thing. Shhh.
I just want to just say one thing important about this, which
is what is really the debate about ממעט הדמות mema'et hadmut as
opposed to שופך דמים? shofech damim? Isn't it all saying it's about
human life? But I read somewhere, I forget who it was, that
said that maybe this is exactly what's at the heart of בית
שמאי Beit Shammai that says two boys. Like why is it saying
two boys? Like what does it, we've never really explained what logic
that means, you know, other than saying, okay, in rabbinic culture Ben
were, were preferred over women and so on. But still, what's about
it? But the point is if you think specifically also, you know,
if men are seen as a, the primary ones who are learning
Torah and the primary ones who are doing מצוות, mitzvot, right? So,
and if you focus on בצלם אלוהים, betzelem Elokim, right? And you
focus on sort of like the value of bringing human life because
of the way it brings God into the world. Okay. And then
you, so then you might want to say well then boys are
preferred to girls because boys do more Torah, or men do more
Torah, men do more מצוות mitzvot and so on. You know, and
that, so I think that there could really be a very serious
correspondence there. I, that to me is a very persuasive way of
explaining בית שמאי Beit Shammai and also of understanding the difference, whether
the point, whether you say שופך דם shofech dam or, or you
know, ממעט הדמות. mema'et hadmut. Isn't it both saying life? Yeah, but
life from a different perspective, biological life or life as a way
of God's presence, which might make you look... We had an earlier
discussion about is there a מצווה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru urevu
for non-Jews? Even though the פסוקים pesukim, seem pretty explicit. Right? So
how are you focusing? You're focusing on bringing God into the world
might lead you one way, focusing on just bringing life into the
world right another way. So there really is a serious difference here.
Let's just read to the משנה, Mishna, just give me two more
minutes. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. ובנחה יאמר שובה ה' רבבות אלפי ישראל.
Uvenucho yomar shuva Hashem rivvot alfei Yisrael. God returned to the myriads
of the thousands of Israel. מלמד שאין השכינה שורה על פחות משני
אלפים ושני רבבות מישראל. Melamed she'ein haShechina shora al pachos mishnei alafim
ushnei rivvavos miYisrael. So the שכינה Shechina doesn't rest on less than
two thousand and two myriads, which is twenty thousand, twenty-two thousand, right,
of Israel. הרי שהיו ישראל שני אלפים ושני רבבות חסר אחד. Harei
shehayu Yisrael shnei alafim ushnei rivvavos chaser echad. Let's say they were
21,999. וזה, veze, I hope it doesn't mean total, anyway, in one
place or something, וזה לא עסק בפריה ורביה, veze lo asak befirya
verivya, and this person didn't, wasn't into פרו ורבו. pru urevu. נמצא
זה גורם לשכינה שתסתלק מישראל. Nimtza ze gorem laShechina shetistalek miYisrael. So
because of the one kid you didn't have, that's why there wasn't
a שכינה Shechina in Israel. So that's really the type of ממעט
הדמות mema'et hadmut of bringing God. presence into the world.
So and again notice the emphasis on ישראל, Yisrael, right? אבל חננא
אומר aval Chanana omer משום רבי אליעזר mishum Rabbi Eliezer חייב מיתה
chayav mitah שנאמר ובנים לא היו להם she-ne'emar u-vanim lo hayu lahem
by what was it אלעזר ואיתמר Elazar ve-Itamar נדב ואביהוא. Nadav ve-Avihu.
נדב ואביהוא, Nadav ve-Avihu, right? נדב ואביהוא, Nadav ve-Avihu, yeah. נדב
ואביהוא.
Nadav ve-Avihu.
ההיו להם בנים לא מתו, ha-hayu lahem banim lo metu, which is
not
פשט pshat of the פסוקים, but okay. אחרים אומרים acherim omrim גורם
לשכינה שתסתלק מישראל gorem la-shechinah she-tistalek mi-yisrael שנאמר להיות לך לאלוקים ולזרעך
אחריך. she-ne'emar lihyot lecha l'Elokim u-l'zaracha acharecha. בזמן שזרעך אחריך bi-zman she-zaracha
acharecha השכינה שורה. ha-shechinah shorah. Then the שכינה shechinah continues. אין זרעך
אחריך, ein zaracha acharecha, if you don't, על מי שורה? al mi
shorah? Where should God's presence reside? על העצים ועל האבנים, al ha-eitzim
v'al ha-avanim, maybe on the sticks and the stones? So for there
to be continuity. And again this also points towards, I would say,
the boys because obviously you don't biologically have later generations without boys
and girls, but in a patriarchy, it's אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak
v'Yaakov. The sense of זרעך אחריך zaracha acharecha is not about the
girls that אברהם Avraham is going to have or that יצחק Yitzchak
or יעקב Yaakov are going to have. It's about the boys, right?
So that also sort of points the way בית שמאי Beit Shammai
way of thinking about it. And the last thing to say is,
I think that the על העצים ועל האבנים al ha-eitzim v'al ha-avanim
is a little bit of an echo because there's a גמרא that
says that, no, no, no, I wasn't going to say that. There's
a גמרא that speaks about the idea of masturbation,
that it's as if you, you know, waste the seed על העצים
ועל האבנים. al ha-eitzim v'al ha-avanim. So I think that that might
be being a little bit echoed. If you're not having children with
your seed, you know, where's it going and where do you expect
the divine presence to rest? Okay. דאיתמר d'itmar between worrying about the
future, I
heard a secular economist on the radio this morning who